A Guide to the Papers of Admiral Frank F. Fletcher 1873-1928
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Admiral Frank F. Fletcher 1873-1928
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3484, -a, -b
This collection consists of ca. 1900 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was acquired in installments. The first group (3584) was deposited by Mrs. Philip B. Payton and Mrs. Robert Barnhart on Dec. 14, 1970 and was subsequently changed to a gift of February 25, 1972. The second group (3584-a) was desposited by the ladies on December 20, 1971, and changed to a gift on February 25, 1972. The third group (3584-b) was given as a gift ot the library on February 25, 1972 by Mrs. Peyton and Mrs. Barnhart.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 1900 items, 1873-1928, in 11 Hollinger boxes. It comprises the correspondence, official records and reports, scrapbooks, photographs, and other memorabilia of Frank F. Fletcher during his Naval career in which he attained the rank of Admiral and Commander-in-Chief of the Atlantic Fleet. Also included in this collection is material of Admiral Fletcher's post-Naval career, specifically, his role on the War Industries Board. These papers form an important addition to the study of United States' intervention in Mexico during Woodrow Wilson's terms of office. Admiral Fletcher was in charge of the United States fleet at Veracruz in 1913 and 1914 and his correspondence, officially with the Navy and State Department and unofficially with his wife an daughters, is very rich in describing the diplomatic, military, and political situation in Mexico. Other fields of interest include Naval History, gunnery, and ballistic inventions, and the world cruise of 1905.
Arrangement
The collection has been generally arranged chronologically within specific areas. Where possible the collection was kept in its original order, such as the division into specific areas of Admiral Fletcher's interests. The correspondence is arranged chronologically in two segments, the personal and official correspondence of Admiral Fletcher and the correspondence with his wife and daughters. Other sections, such as scrapbooks, official orders and documents are chronological within their respective boxes.
Contents List
- Personal Correspondence of Admiral Fletcher 1879-1928
  - Correspondence, most concerning Admiral Fletcher's naval inventions and innovations 1879-1910, 25 items (Box 1)
  - Correspondence mainly concerned with the Mexican situation. Includes a Dec. 19 letter from President Wilson's personal envoy to Mexico, John Lind. 1913, 33 items (Box 1)
  - Correspondence consisting of congratulatory pieces on Fletcher's work in Mexico and his impending elevation to Commander-in-Chief 1914 Jan 5 - 1914 June 15, 70 items (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, congratulatory notes to Admiral FLetcher on his elevation to Commander-in-Chief of the Atlantic fleet 1914 June 16- Dec (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, mostly congratulatory notes to Admiral Fletcher on his appointment to the rank of Full Admiral 1915, 60 items (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, mostly concerned with Admiral Fletcher's ideas on disarmament 1916, 17 items (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, many letters concerning Fletcher's role on The War Industries Board 1917-1928, 21 items (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife 1891-1894 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife and mother-in-law 1895 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife and mother-in-law 1896 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his with and mother-in-law 1896 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife 1898 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife 1899 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife 1899 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife 1900 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife and daughter 1901 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife and mother-in-law 1906 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife and daughters 1908 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife and daughters 1912 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife and daughters 1913 Jan- Feb (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife and daughters 1913 March- Sept (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife and daughter 1914 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife and daughter 1914 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife and daughter 1915 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife and daughter 1915 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife 1916 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, Frank F. Fletcher to his wife 1922-1927 (Box 3)
  - Postcards n.d. (Box 3)
- Official Order 1875-1926
  - 1875 Oct. 23 - 1898 July 18, ca. 50 pp. (Box 4)
  - 1898 Oct. 23 - 1913 Nov. 22, ca. 34 pp. (Box 4)
  - 1902 Dec. 6 - 1908 Sept. 9, ca. 43 pp. (Box 4)
  - 1908 Nov. 27 - 1915 March 10, ca. 70 pp. (Box 4)
  - 1914 April 14 - 1920 Oct. 23, ca. 25 pp. (Box 4)
  - 1915 March 10 - 1926 May 21, ca. 35 pp. (Box 4)
  - Binder from Official Records n.d., 1 item
- Official Reports, Broadsides, Photographs re: Mexican Crisis 1913-1914
  - I nstructions for Naval Vessels in Mexican Gulf Ports 1913-1914, 8 pp. (Box 5)
  - Instruction for Naval Vessels in Mexican Gulf Ports 1914, 9 pp. (Box 5)
  - Naval Operations During the Mexican Crisis Protest of American Refugees 1913-1914, 10 pp., TMs (Box 5)
  - Naval Operations During the Mexican Crisis 1913-1914 'Copies of Personal Memoranda...' 1913 Oct. 23- 1913 Dec. 15, ca. 40 pp., TMs (Box 5)
  - Naval Operations During the Mexican Crisis 'Copies of Reports' 1913 Feb.- July, 50 pp., TMs (Box 5)
  - Naval Operations During the Mexican Crisis 1913-1914 'Seizure and Occupation of Vera Cruz April 21st-April 30th 1914' 1914 May 13, 48 pp., TMs (carbon) (Box 5)
  - Fleet Order No. 17-14 Occupation of Vera Cruz1914 April 26, 1 p. (Box 5)
  - Broadsides, Proclaimations by Admiral Fletcher to the people of Vera Cruz 1914 April, 17 items (Box 5)
  - Photographs during the Mexican situation 1913-1914, 36 items (Box 5)
- Records, Diary, Notebooks and genealogical papers of Admiral Fletcher and the Fletcher Family 1873-1919
  - Records of Rear Admiral F.F. Fletcher, U.S.N. 1888-1919, ca. 100 pp. (Box 6)
  - Funeral Sermon on the death of Mr. J.D. Fletcher 1873 Sept., ca. 50 pp. (Box 6)
  - Diary, Cruise of 1905- People I Met and Books I have read1905, 150 pp. (Box 6)
  - Notebook containing notes and sundry information, mathematical problems n.d., 200 pp. (Box 6)
  - Application for membership in the Society of Mayflower Descendants n.d., 12 pp. (Box 6)
  - Fletcher Family Genealogy n.d., 22 items (Box 6)
  - Calling cards and postcards n.d., 57 items (Box 6)
- Notes, Reports, Lectures and Discussion of Admiral Fletcher
  - Notes on Television Transmission n.d., 37 pp., AMs (carbon) (Box 7)
  - Notes on Disarmament, War and League of Nations ca. 1925, 24 pp., AMs (Box 7)
  - two speeches: one before the Banquet of Naval Academy Graduates and the other before a society n.d., 9 pp.,TMs (Box 7)
  - Lecture to the Naval War College, Recent Improvements in Mines and Torpedoes1904 July, ca. 28 pp., TMs (Box 7)
  - Lecture prepared for the Naval War College, Torpedo Boat Attack 1896, ca. 30 pp., TMsS (Box 7)
  - Discussion, The Automobile Torpedo and Its Usesn.d., 6 pp., TMsS (Box 7)
  - Record of Medal of Honor Recipients 1862-1917, 125 pp. (Box 7)
  - Plan to Achieve and Preserve the Peace of the World n.d., 23 pp., TMs (Box 7)
  - Notes on The Maritime Conference and Range Lights at Sean.d., 8 pp., AMs (Box 7)
  - International Law Situations calling for decision or action by Naval Officers n.d., 5 pp., TMs (Box 7)
  - Memorandum Upon Moving Target Practice 1909, 4 pp., TMs (Box 7)
  - Index to Admiral's Files 1913 June 8- 1915 Dec. 7, 2 pp. (Box 7)
  - Lecture, Guns, Armor, and Speed n.d., 6 pp. (Box 7)
  - Photographs n.d., 58 items (Box 7)
  - Fletcher to Baruch, Report of Navy Representative of the War Industries Board1918 Nov. 22, 8 pp., TMsS (Box 7)
  - Sketchboook from the Cruise of the Ticonderoga ca. 1875 (Box 7)
- Scrapbooks
  - Black scrapbook containing mostly invitations and calling cards 1912-1916 (Box 8)
  - Brown scrapbook containing newspaper clippings 1898-1912 (Box 8)
  - Echoes of Official Entertainment 1908-1916 (Box 9)
  - Red scrapbook compiled by May Foster 1913-1914 (Box 10)
  - Black scrapbook, Echoes of Official Entertainment 1915-1919 (Box 10)
- 8 letters of greeting and friendship 1899-1935 (Box 11)
- a. 45 photographs primarily of Admiral Fletcher's naval career, i.e. ships he sailed, places he visited, India and Mexico, photos of himself and shipmates n.d. (Box 11)
- 1 packet of material concerning the christening of the U.S.S. Fletcher by Mrs. Fletcher n.d. (Box 11)
- (miscellaneous): Naval Academy grades, blueprints and drawings of his inventions, news clippings, passports, etc. n.d., ca. 10 items (Box 11)
- One bronze nameplate inscribed Rear Admiral Fletchern.d. (Box 11)
- Green scrapbooks, Printed Material, Photographs and Microfilm
  - 1910-1912 (Box 11)
  - 1912-1914 (Box 11)
  - 1913 Nov. - 1914 May (Box 11)
  - 1914 Jan. - 1914 May (Box 11)
  - 1914 May - 1914 Sept. (Box 11)
  - 1914 June - 1914 Dec (Box 11)
  - 1914 Sept. - 1915 May (Box 11)
  - 1915 Dec. - 1915 June (Box 11)
  - 1916 Jan. - 1916 April (Box 11)
  - 1916 May - 1918 July (Box 11)
  - The United States Navy from the Revolution to Date 1915, 140 pp. (Box 11)
  - Photographs, Admiral Fletcher and Admiral Mayo n.d., 8 items (Box 11)
  - Roll of Microfilm. Copies of photograph of Admiral Fletcher reviewing the troops n.d. (Box 11)
- Document Collection 1878-1926
  - Ensign's Commission 1878 Feb. 8
  - Lieutenant's Commission 1889 April 1
  - Columbian Exposition Citation 1895 May 15
  - Lieutenant Commander's Commission 1899 April 24
  - Commander's Commission 1904 March 30
  - Captain's Commission 1908 May 22
  - Rear Admiral's Commission 1911 Nov. 2
  - Rear Admiral's Commission 1911 Dec. 20
  - Welcome to New Orleans 1912 Dec.
  - War Industries Board Citation 1918 Dec. 30
  - Distinguished Service Medal Citation 1926 Feb. 9